<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Timothy Oh</title>
<link>https://alskaf1293.github.io/my-blog/</link>
<atom:link href="https://alskaf1293.github.io/my-blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.8.27</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Crossroads</title>
  <link>https://alskaf1293.github.io/my-blog/posts/post8/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Over the past few days, I’ve been talking to some friends about this sort of mini crisis that I’m having. In being interested in active matter, I thought that understanding theoretical condensed matter would probably be a good thing to do. You don’t need every aspect of theoretical condensed matter physics to do work in active matter - it’s probably overkill. In fact, I think the expertise of a chemist is probably more suited for work in condensed matter than a theoretical physicist. But this has encouraged my pursuit in learning theoretical physics anyways - for the reasons that 1. I’m interested in theoretical physics and 2. I know that it will be useful in my pursuit of AI down the line. However, there is another problem that has caught my attention, which is quantum gravity. Quantum gravity is interesting as a problem, first because it’s literally a theory of everything. If one were able to produce such a theory that unifies the Standard Model as well as gravity, you’d essentially have a theory of everything - one model that when given the parameters would tell you how the universe evolves. Being ambitious, this obvious sounds like something interesting to work on. So part of my recent struggles has been attempting to reconcile these two interests: my pursuit of artificial intelligence and this problem of quantum gravity. After much toil and thinking, I’m thinking that it probably can’t be done. At least, with my current viewpoints on how AI progress should be made as well as the nature of QG. They’re just too different. Let me elaborate on how I view both of these.</p>
<p>My current perspective on artificial intelligence is that everyone is too LLM-pilled. Alot of time and effort has gone to studying these systems which granted, given their very impressive results since they were first released in 2017 as well as their subsequent scaling by OpenAI and various other companies has led to systems that can perform well on quite alot of tasks. To name some, I’ll include essay writing, image generation/art (not exactly LLM based but can be combined with LLM querying), generally complex reasoning (solving complex maths, physics, and other science problems). I think I should even improve on my own understanding of LLMs - even though I can code them there’s still alot of theory to be learned. Although with these tremendous advantages artificial systems still have a whole slew of tasks that they suck at compared to humans. These include sensorimotor tasks (how would one even solve sensotimor tasks with LLMS?), commonsense reasoning, and general creativity and pattern recognition. These observations can be summarized by Moravec’s Paradox. It almost seems like there’s a sort of “mutual orthogonality” of computational tasks that are solved by two parallel systems - one that’s the digital computer, and the other the human brain.</p>
<p>Moravec’s Paradox has been a subject of both fascination and an integral part of my own research recently. The hypothesis is that the cause for it is due to the two different hardware systems that computational tasks are performed on. In other words, hardware is the issue. The paradox has been observed in every computational task that has been optimized on digital computers, and this fact has not changed since their inception in the 50s. Without going into too much detail, I forsee a revolution where the hardware is completely overturned, both in terms of the computational model that they implement as well as the materials that constitute them, possibly expanding to areas where the dominant computers are not made with silicon but something more exotic or unconventional by today’s standards (photonics is an interesting direction). Hence my interest in condensed matter - being well educated in how materials work is part of my desire to bring about this revolution.</p>
<p>My motivation in high energy theoretical physics is completely independent from AI. As interesting as the problem of QG is, I don’t think it can be reconciled with pursing artificial intelligence. Understanding quantum gravity first of all, requires an understanding of exotic mathematical structures, an understanding of the Standard Model and quantum field theory which would take me more years to develop, as well as an understanding of the current approaches such as string theory and lqg and their possible flaws. While I could very well forsee myself learning all of these things, it would certainly take out of my AI ambitions. They’re just along two different axes - one is in the land of theory and mathematics, the other in the axis of engineering and computer science. It is a sad but unofortunate reality - that I’d be spreading myself too thin if I tried to do both. For now, the two paths are along the same axes - quantum field theory (as established by my discussion before), but at some point I will have to step back to the AI path. Maybe during retirement I can return to this - if it hasn’t been solved already. Maybe.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>blog</category>
  <guid>https://alskaf1293.github.io/my-blog/posts/post8/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 18 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Non Degenerate First Order Perturbation Theory</title>
  <link>https://alskaf1293.github.io/my-blog/posts/post7/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Perturbation theory is the study of solving problems that are almost solvable, where the system that you’re trying to solve for is close to one that can be solved exactly.</p>
<p>First, we start with nondegenerate perturbation theory, where</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0AH_%7B0%7D%20%5Cket%7Bn%5E%7B(0)%7D%7D%20=%20E%5E%7B(0)%7D_n%20%5Cket%7Bn%5E%7B(0)%7D%7D%0A"></p>
<p>where the nondegeneracy condition requires that</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0AE%5E%7B(0)%7D_n%20%5Cneq%20E%5E%7B(0)%7D_m%0A"></p>
<p>for all <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?n%20%5Cneq%20m">. We start from the time independent Schrodinger equation in operator form</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0AH%5Cket%7Bn%7D=E_n%20%5Cket%7Bn%7D%0A"></p>
<p>where our Hamiltonian is expanded in terms of the perturbation parameterized by <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Clambda"></p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0AH=H_0+%5Clambda%20V%0A"></p>
<p>It’s important to note here that V is not the potential, but the pertubation that we are adding to see how our energies and solutions are affected. \</p>
<p>The idea then is to expand the energies and solution kets in a power series</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0AE_n=E%5E%7B(0)%7D_n+%5Clambda%20E%5E%7B(1)%7D_n+%5Clambda%5E2%20E%5E%7B(2)%7D_n%20+%20%5Cdots%0A"></p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Cket%7Bn%7D=%5Cket%7Bn%5E%7B(0)%7D%7D+%5Clambda%20%5Cket%7Bn%5E%7B(1)%7D%7D+%5Clambda%5E2%20%5Cket%7Bn%5E%7B(2)%7D%7D%20+%20%5Cdots%0A"></p>
<p>Plugging these relations back into the time independent Schrodinger Equation</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A(H_0+%5Clambda%20V)(%5Cket%7Bn%5E%7B(0)%7D%7D+%5Clambda%20%5Cket%7Bn%5E%7B(1)%7D%7D+%5Clambda%5E2%20%5Cket%7Bn%5E%7B(2)%7D%7D%20+%20%5Cdots)%0A=(E%5E%7B(0)%7D_n+%5Clambda%20E%5E%7B(1)%7D_n+%5Clambda%5E2%20E%5E%7B(2)%7D_n%20+%20%5Cdots)(%5Cket%7Bn%5E%7B(0)%7D%7D+%5Clambda%20%5Cket%7Bn%5E%7B(1)%7D%7D+%5Clambda%5E2%20%5Cket%7Bn%5E%7B(2)%7D%7D%20+%20%5Cdots)%0A"></p>
<p>If you expand this out, well the terms would be infinite. However, we can group this expansion in terms of their order in <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Clambda">.</p>
<p><strong>First order non degenerate perturbation theory</strong></p>
<p>For first order perturbation theory, we only consider the terms above that are linear in <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Clambda">. Expanding it out, we have that in order 0 in <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Clambda">, we have</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0AH_0%5Cket%7Bn%5E%7B(0)%7D%7D=E%5E%7B(0)%7D_n%5Cket%7Bn%5E%7B(0)%7D%7D%0A"></p>
<p>which we have taken to already be true. For order 1 in <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Clambda">, we have</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0AV%5Cket%7Bn%5E%7B(0)%7D%7D+H_0%5Cket%7Bn%5E%7B(1)%7D%7D=E%5E%7B(0)%7D_n%5Cket%7Bn%5E%7B(1)%7D%7D+E%5E%7B(1)%7D_n%5Cket%7Bn%5E%7B(0)%7D%7D%0A"></p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A(V-E%5E%7B(1)%7D_n)%5Cket%7Bn%5E%7B(0)%7D%7D=(E%5E%7B(0)%7D_n-H_0)%5Cket%7Bn%5E%7B(1)%7D%7D%0A"></p>
<p>Taking the inner product, we have</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Cbra%7Bn%5E%7B(0)%7D%7D(V-E%5E%7B(1)%7D_n)%5Cket%7Bn%5E%7B(0)%7D%7D=%5Cbra%7Bn%5E%7B(0)%7D%7D(E%5E%7B(0)%7D_n-H_0)%5Cket%7Bn%5E%7B(1)%7D%7D%0A"></p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Cbra%7Bn%5E%7B(0)%7D%7DV%5Cket%7Bn%5E%7B(0)%7D%7D-E%5E%7B(1)%7D_n=0%0A"></p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Cboxed%7BE%5E%7B(1)%7D_n=%5Cbra%7Bn%5E%7B(0)%7D%7DV%5Cket%7Bn%5E%7B(0)%7D%7D%7D%0A"></p>
<p>The first order energy correction. To find the expression for the first order solution correction <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cket%7Bn%5E%7B(1)%7D%7D"> we start from the order 1 expression again</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0AV%5Cket%7Bn%5E%7B(0)%7D%7D+H_0%5Cket%7Bn%5E%7B(1)%7D%7D=E%5E%7B(0)%7D_n%5Cket%7Bn%5E%7B(1)%7D%7D+E%5E%7B(1)%7D_n%5Cket%7Bn%5E%7B(0)%7D%7D%0A"></p>
<p>Multiply both sides by <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cbra%7Bm%5E%7B0%7D%7D"> where <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?m%20%5Cneq%20n"></p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Cbra%7Bm%5E%7B0%7D%7DV%5Cket%7Bn%5E%7B(0)%7D%7D+%5Cbra%7Bm%5E%7B0%7D%7DH_0%5Cket%7Bn%5E%7B(1)%7D%7D=%5Cbra%7Bm%5E%7B0%7D%7DE%5E%7B(0)%7D_n%5Cket%7Bn%5E%7B(1)%7D%7D+%5Cbra%7Bm%5E%7B0%7D%7DE%5E%7B(1)%7D_n%5Cket%7Bn%5E%7B(0)%7D%7D%0A"></p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Cbra%7Bm%5E%7B0%7D%7DV%5Cket%7Bn%5E%7B(0)%7D%7D+E%5E%7B(0)%7D_m%5Cbraket%7Bm%5E%7B0%7D%7Cn%5E%7B(1)%7D%7D=E%5E%7B(0)%7D_n%5Cbraket%7Bm%5E%7B0%7D%7Cn%5E%7B(1)%7D%7D%0A"></p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Cbra%7Bm%5E%7B0%7D%7DV%5Cket%7Bn%5E%7B(0)%7D%7D=(E%5E%7B(0)%7D_n-E%5E%7B(0)%7D_m)%5Cbraket%7Bm%5E%7B0%7D%7Cn%5E%7B(1)%7D%7D%0A"></p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Cbraket%7Bm%5E%7B0%7D%7Cn%5E%7B(1)%7D%7D=%5Cfrac%7B%5Cbra%7Bm%5E%7B0%7D%7DV%5Cket%7Bn%5E%7B(0)%7D%7D%7D%7B(E%5E%7B(0)%7D_n-E%5E%7B(0)%7D_m)%7D%0A"></p>
<p>With some arguments, if we impose that <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cbraket%7Bn%5E%7B(0)%7D%7Cn%7D=1">, then <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cbraket%7Bn%5E%7B(0)%7D%7Cn%5E%7B(1)%7D%7D=0"> and we have</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Cboxed%7B%5Cket%7Bn%5E%7B(1)%7D%7D%20=%20%5Csum_%7Bm%20%5Cneq%20n%7D%20%5Cfrac%7B%5Cbra%7Bm%5E%7B(0)%7D%7D%20V%20%5Cket%7Bn%5E%7B(0)%7D%7D%7D%7BE_n%5E%7B(0)%7D%20-%20E_m%5E%7B(0)%7D%7D%20%5Cket%7Bm%5E%7B(0)%7D%7D%7D%0A"></p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>quantum mechanics</category>
  <guid>https://alskaf1293.github.io/my-blog/posts/post7/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Derivation of the Klein Gordon Equation</title>
  <link>https://alskaf1293.github.io/my-blog/posts/post6/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>In classical mechanics, the total energy of a system can be written as</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0AE%20=%20T%20+%20V%20=%20%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7B2%7D%20mv%5E2%20+%20V%20=%20%5Cfrac%7Bp%5E2%7D%7B2m%7D%20+%20V%0A"></p>
<p>where <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?T"> and <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?V"> are the kinetic and potential energy of a system, respectively. In quantum mechanics, we promote these classical variables to Hermitian operators, where we use the standard substitutions in the position basis are</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Chat%7BE%7D%20=%20i%20%5Chbar%20%5Cfrac%7B%5Cpartial%7D%7B%5Cpartial%20t%7D%0A"></p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Chat%7Bp%7D%20=%20-%20i%20%5Chbar%20%5Cnabla%0A"></p>
<p>and the energy relation becomes</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0Ai%20%5Chbar%20%5Cfrac%7B%5Cpartial%7D%7B%5Cpartial%20t%7D%20=%20-%5Cfrac%7B%5Chbar%5E2%7D%7B2m%7D%5Cnabla%5E2+V%0A"></p>
<p>and multiplication of the wavefunction <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cpsi"> yields</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0Ai%20%5Chbar%20%5Cfrac%7B%5Cpartial%20%5Cpsi%7D%7B%5Cpartial%20t%7D%20=%20(-%5Cfrac%7B%5Chbar%5E2%7D%7B2m%7D%5Cnabla%5E2+V)%20%5Cpsi%0A"></p>
<p>the Schrodinger Equation. For the free particle, we can forget about <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?V"> and the relation reduces to</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0Ai%20%5Chbar%20%5Cfrac%7B%5Cpartial%20%5Cpsi%7D%7B%5Cpartial%20t%7D%20=%20-%5Cfrac%7B%5Chbar%5E2%7D%7B2m%7D%5Cnabla%5E2%20%5Cpsi%0A"></p>
<p>We derived this from a non-relativistic nergy relation. To introduce relativity into our theory, we can instead start from the relativistic energy relation for a free particle</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0AE%5E2%20=%20p%5E2c%5E2%20+%20m%5E2c%5E4%0A"></p>
<p>and plug in our operators as before</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A-%20%5Chbar%5E2%20%5Cfrac%7B%5Cpartial%5E2%7D%7B%5Cpartial%20t%5E2%7D%20=%20-%5Chbar%5E2%20%5Cnabla%5E2%20c%5E2%20+%20m%5E2%20c%5E4%0A"></p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A-%20%5Chbar%5E2%20%5Cfrac%7B%5Cpartial%5E2%7D%7B%5Cpartial%20t%5E2%7D%5Cpsi%20=%20(-%5Chbar%5E2%20%5Cnabla%5E2%20c%5E2%20+%20m%5E2%20c%5E4)%20%5Cpsi%0A"></p>
<p>Rearranging yields</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A(%5Chbar%5E2%20%5Cfrac%7B%5Cpartial%5E2%7D%7B%5Cpartial%20t%5E2%7D-%5Chbar%5E2%20%5Cnabla%5E2%20c%5E2%20+%20m%5E2%20c%5E4)%20%5Cpsi%20=%200%0A"></p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A(%5Cfrac%7B1%7D%7Bc%5E2%7D%20%5Cfrac%7B%5Cpartial%5E2%7D%7B%5Cpartial%20t%5E2%7D-%20%5Cnabla%5E2%20+%20%5Cfrac%7Bm%5E2%20c%5E2%7D%7B%5Chbar%5E2%7D)%20%5Cpsi%20=%200%0A"></p>
<p>This is known a the Klein-Gordon equation. Historically, other physicists at the time were pretty well satisfied with this equation as a relativistic version of the Schrodinger Equation. However, a clever man by the name of Paul Dirac thought that there were problems with this equation. Firstly, it was second order in time, which means that you’d need to know the initial state <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cpsi(0)"> and it’s first derivative <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cpsi'(0)"> in order to evolve it in time. Secondly, for reasons that I won’t get into here, being second order in time means that interpreting the probability of the Klein Gordon equation allows negative probability, which is nonsensical.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>quantum mechanics</category>
  <guid>https://alskaf1293.github.io/my-blog/posts/post6/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Distribution Shift Problem in LLMs</title>
  <link>https://alskaf1293.github.io/my-blog/posts/post5/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>In preparation for graduate school and future research, I have decided to learn more about statistical learning theory, which is an area of machine learning that I haven’t really looked at up until now. An interesting case study is the problem of LLM hallucination, which is a problem that any person who has spent a sufficient amount of time around chatbots has probably encountered.</p>
<p>An LLM is self-supervised learning mechanism, where a model learns to predict the next token given a sequence of previous tokens. The sentence “The current president is Donald” should be met with an output token of “Trump”. In reality, these tokens usually aren’t words, but character bits (ie. ‘ae’, ‘ee’, ‘e’, etc.) and the bits to use in the dictionary is decided by information theory.</p>
<p>Let</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?X"> be the space of possible token sequences</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?Y"> be the space of possible next tokens</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?P_%7B%5Ctext%7Btrain%7D%7D(x,y)"> be the training distribution</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?P_%7B%5Ctheta%7D(y%20%7C%20x)"> be the conditional distribution over the next token sequences given a sequence</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cmathcal%7BL%7D(%5Ctheta)%20=%20%5Cmathbb%7BE%7D_%7B(x,y)%20%5Csim%20P_%7Btrain%7D(x,y)%7D%5B-%5Clog%20P_%7B%5Ctheta%7D(y%20%5Cmid%20x)%5D"></p>
<p>In machine learning, the model minimizes <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cmathcal%7BL%7D"> over time. The so called “out of distribution” problem happens upon deployment, when</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0AP_%7B%5Ctext%7Btrain%7D%7D(x,y)%20%5Cneq%20P_%7B%5Ctext%7Btest%7D%7D(x,y)%0A"></p>
<p>which yields hallucination and inability to derive new science. This is in contrast the assumption that underlies most theoretical and experimental machine learning that the testing and training distribution are the same. A measure for this distribution difference can be given by the Kullback-Leibler divergence</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0AD_%7B%5Cmathrm%7BKL%7D%7D(P_%7B%5Ctext%7Btrain%7D%7D%20%5C,%5C%7C%5C,%20P_%7B%5Ctext%7Btest%7D%7D)%0A"></p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>artificial intelligence</category>
  <guid>https://alskaf1293.github.io/my-blog/posts/post5/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The completeness relation in quantum mechanics</title>
  <link>https://alskaf1293.github.io/my-blog/posts/post4/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>A very simple but useful relation in quantum mechanics is the so called completeness relation. Here, I will derive it</p>
<p>For any <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cket%7B%5Cpsi%7D"> living in a Hilbert space, you can represent the vector as a linear combination of some orthonormal bases</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Cket%7B%5Cpsi%7D%20=%20%5Csum_%7Bi%7D%20c_%7B%5Calpha_i%7D%20%5Cket%7B%5Calpha_i%7D%0A"></p>
<p>For any one of these orthonormal bases, applying the bra <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cbra%7B%5Calpha_k%7D"> with the orthonormality condition <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cbraket%7B%5Calpha_i%20%7C%20%5Calpha_j%7D%20=%20%5Cdelta_%7Bij%7D"></p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Cbraket%7B%5Calpha_k%20%7C%20%5Cpsi%7D%20=%20%5Cbra%7B%5Calpha_k%7D%20(%5Csum_%7Bi%7D%20c_%7B%5Calpha_i%7D%20%5Cket%7B%5Calpha_i%7D)%0A"></p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Cbraket%7B%5Calpha_k%20%7C%20%5Cpsi%7D%20=%20c_%7B%5Calpha_k%7D%0A"></p>
<p>So we can rewrite this</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Cket%7B%5Cpsi%7D%20=%20%5Csum_%7Bi%7D%20c_%7B%5Calpha_i%7D%20%5Cket%7B%5Calpha_i%7D%0A"></p>
<p>as</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Cket%7B%5Cpsi%7D%20=%20%5Csum_%7Bi%7D%20%5Cket%7B%5Calpha_i%7D%20%5Cbraket%7B%5Calpha_i%20%7C%20%5Cpsi%7D%0A"></p>
<p>Since <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cket%7B%5Cpsi%7D"> is arbitrary, we have</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Cmathbb%7BI%7D%20=%20%5Csum_%7Bi%7D%20%5Cket%7B%5Calpha_i%7D%20%5Cbra%7B%5Calpha_i%7D%0A"></p>
<p>The completeness relation. For the continuous case, you have the integral</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Cmathbb%7BI%7D%20=%20%5Cint%20da%20%5Cket%7Ba%7D%20%5Cbra%7Ba%7D%0A"></p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>quantum mechanics</category>
  <guid>https://alskaf1293.github.io/my-blog/posts/post4/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Differences Between the Computer and the Brain</title>
  <link>https://alskaf1293.github.io/my-blog/posts/post2/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I’ve recently just finished reading the book “The Computer and The Brain” by John Von Neumann. A brilliant physicist, he contributed a great many things to quantum mechanics, mathematics, economics, and computer science. The book that he wrote was his opinions and observations on the differences between hardware of the digital computers that had at the time, only recently began being developed and the biological “wetware” that is the brain. Interestingly, this book was a collection of his notes that he was working on just before he died. It may very well be the case that he could have had alot more to say.</p>
<p>Here I’m going to talk about some major points that I thought were interesting in the book, as well as a comparison between how the technology looked back then and the developments that have been made since.</p>
<ul>
<li>Error Resilience as a Trade off of Precision</li>
</ul>
<p>In the book, von Neumann highlights an interesting thought: that error resilience is a trade off of precision. To elaborate on this, one could consider a digital machine. In any such machine, the execution of said machine depends on the information stored in memory and the specific sequence of instructions that the computer executes. It’s imperative that these digits are to be represented exactly as the programmer intends. In the case that one is flipped (say from a cosmic particle or something) could change the value of a store number entirely or possibly even crash a program. The brain, on the other hand, is not as vulnerable to tiny perturbations. A spike recieved at time <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t"> will not differ in a very meaningful way if that spike were offset to time <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?t+%5CDelta%20t"> for some small <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5CDelta%20t">. It should be noted that this noise tolerance comes at a tradeoff of precision.</p>
<p>To consider what exactly we mean by precision, we can consider the quantity of jitter. Suppose we have a spike train denoted by the times <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5C%7B%20t_0,%20t_1,%20%5Cdots,%20t_k%5C%7D">. We can take the interspike intervals and group them into another list <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5C%7Bi_0,%20i_1,%20%5Cdots,%20i_%7Bk-1%7D%5C%7D">. Taking the standard deviation of this list we have jitter. We can use this as a measure of timing precision in a neuron. In contrast, a clock edge in a digital computer must have a jitter of <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?10%5E%7B-12%7D"> seconds, otherwise the effects cascade downards and calculations get messed up. Comparing this with the precision of a neuron, is a difference in 9 orders of magnitude. Clearly, the neuron’s timing fidelity is much less sensitive than a digital computer is required to be.</p>
<ul>
<li>Serial versus Parallel Organization and Architecture Differences</li>
</ul>
<p>Digital programs (typically) execute programs sequentially, reflecting its serial nature. Brains on the other hand operate in millisecond level precisions as we have established. Despite this seemingly superior advantage of digital computers, parallelism is what makes the brain able to create rich, semantic representations. Control is decentralized, and computation arises from large networks of activity rather than symbolic manipulation.</p>
<p>The von Neumann machine has separated memory and computation units, whereas the brain has them encoded into the same fundamental unit. Synapses store long term data, neurons both compute and store nonlinearities.</p>
<ul>
<li>Different Notational Systems and Short Codes</li>
</ul>
<p>Neumann estimated t</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A"></p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>artificial intelligence</category>
  <guid>https://alskaf1293.github.io/my-blog/posts/post2/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Expectation Value of An Observable in Quantum mechanics</title>
  <link>https://alskaf1293.github.io/my-blog/posts/post3/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>In quantum mechanics, an observable is given by the Hermitian operator <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Chat%7BQ%7D">. The expectation value of said observable is given by</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Clangle%20Q%20%5Crangle%20=%20%5Cbra%7B%5Cpsi%7D%20%5Chat%7BQ%7D%20%5Cket%7B%5Cpsi%7D%0A"></p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cket%7B%5Cpsi%7D"> can be expanded in the basis of the observable, given with the coefficients</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Cket%7B%5Cpsi%7D%20=%20c_1%5Cket%7Bq_1%7D%20+%20c_2%5Cket%7Bq_2%7D%20+%20%5Cdots%20+%20c_k%20%5Cket%7Bq_k%7D%0A"></p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Chat%7BQ%7D%5Cket%7B%5Cpsi%7D%20=%20%5Chat%7BQ%7D(c_1%5Cket%7Bq_1%7D%20+%20c_2%5Cket%7Bq_2%7D%20+%20%5Cdots%20+%20c_k%20%5Cket%7Bq_k%7D)%0A"> and given with the observable relation <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Chat%7BQ%7D%5Cket%7Bq_j%7D%20=%20q_j%5Cket%7Bq_j%7D">, we have</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Cbra%7B%5Cpsi%7D%20%5Chat%7BQ%7D%20%5Cket%7B%5Cpsi%7D%20=%20(c%5E*_1%5Cbra%7Bq_1%7D%20+%20c%5E*_2%5Cbra%7Bq_2%7D%20+%20%5Cdots%20+%20c%5E*_k%20%5Cbra%7Bq_k%7D)%20%5Cleft(c_1%20q_1%5Cket%7Bq_1%7D%20+%20c_2%20q_2%5Cket%7Bq_2%7D%20+%20%5Cdots%20+%20c_k%20q_k%5Cket%7Bq_k%7D%20%5Cright)%20%5C%5C%0A"></p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Clangle%20Q%20%5Crangle%20=%20%5Csum_%7Bi,j%7D%20c%5E*_i%20c_j%20q_j%20%5Cbraket%7Bq_i%7Cq_j%7D%0A"></p>
<p>and using the orthonormality condition <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cbraket%7Bq_i%7Cq_j%7D%20=%20%5Cdelta_%7Bij%7D">, we have</p>
<p><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Clangle%20Q%20%5Crangle%20=%20%5Csum_%7Bj%7D%20%7Cc_j%7C%5E2%20q_j%0A"></p>
<p>This corresponds exactly to the expectation value equation.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>quantum mechanics</category>
  <guid>https://alskaf1293.github.io/my-blog/posts/post3/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
